RG 134, Connecticut Council of Churches and Religious Education
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut Council of Churches and Religious Education records
1832-1997
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut Council of Churches and Religious Education
6.25 cubic feet
The Connecticut Council of Churches and Religious Education was formed "to promote and extend the Christian religion in Connecticut by furnishing an interdenominational agency for cooperation in Christian education, comity, and social relations". Contains minutes, treasurer's records, convention records, printed materials, reports and statistics of the Connecticut Federation of Churches, Connecticut Sunday School Union, Connecticut Sunday School Teachers Association, Connecticut Sunday School Association, Connecticut Council of Religious Education, Highland Auxiliary of the Connecticut Sunday School Association, North Tolland Sunday School Association, Professional Religious Education Association, and Connecticut Council of Churches.
RG134
1944-003; 2011-085; 2011-086; 2014-012
Historical Note
The Connecticut Council of Churches and Religious Education was formed "to promote and extend the Christian religion in Connecticut by furnishing an interdenominational agency for cooperation in Christian education, comity, and social relations" (Constitution). The Council functions as the accredited auxiliary of The International Council of Religious Education and maintains associate relations with The Federal Council of Churches of Christ of America. It resulted from a merger in 1932 of The Connecticut Council of Religious Education and the Connecticut Federation of Churches. Hartford County Superior Court on January 22, 1948, granted an application for change of name of the organization from "The Connecticut Council of Churches and Religious Education" to "The Connecticut Council of Churches, Incorporated."
Sunday School conventions in Connecticut originated in 1857 with the first State Convention held at Hartford. Subsequently the Connecticut Association of the American Sunday School Union was formed. In 1871 the Connecticut Sunday School Teachers Association was organized which in 1886 became the Connecticut Sunday School Association. Their Executive Committee meeting minutes of April 8, 1924, state a proposed change in the name of the organization from "The Connecticut Sunday School Association" to "The Connecticut Council of Religious Education."
Scope and Content
Contains minutes, treasurer's records, convention records, printed materials, reports and statistics of the Connecticut Federation of Churches, Connecticut Sunday School Union, Connecticut Sunday School Teachers Association, Connecticut Sunday School Association, Connecticut Council of Religious Education, Highland Auxiliary of the Connecticut Sunday School Association, North Tolland Sunday School Association, Professional Religious Education Association, and Connecticut Council of Churches.
Related Material
None.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut Council of Churches and Religious Education; Connecticut Federation of Churches; Connecticut Sunday School Union; Connecticut Sunday School Teachers Association; Connecticut Sunday School Association; Connecticut Council of Religious Education; Connecticut Council of Churches
Places:
Connecticut -- Church history; Tolland (Conn.) -- Church history; Bolton (Conn.); Coventry (Conn.); Ellington (Conn.); East Windsor (Conn.); Manchester (Conn.) -- Church history; South Windsor (Conn.); Vernon (Conn.); Hartford (Conn.)
Subjects:
Connecticut Council of Churches and Religious Education -- Records and correspondence; Religious education -- Connecticut; Sunday school conventions
Document Types:
Reports; Minutes; Financial records; Pamphlets; Programs; Periodicals; Publications
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Provenance
The records were received on February 10, 1944, from the Reverend Everitt A. Babcock, General Secretary of the Connecticut Council of Churches. Accessions 2011-085 and 2011-086 were donated by the Union Congregational Church to the Connecticut State Library in 2010. Accession 2014-012 was donated by the Connecticut Historical Society to the Connecticut State Library on June 11, 2013.
Container List
- Series 1. Connecticut Federation of Churches, 1911-1932
  - Minutes, 1920-1932; 1 binder (Box 1)
  - Committee on Comity minutes, 1914-1921; 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Treasurer's records (Box 2)
    - 1911-1921, 1 volume (Box 2)
    - 1921-1929, 1 volume (Box 2)
- Series 2. Connecticut Sunday School Union, 1832-1916
  - Dedication of the Beaver Brook Union Sunday School chapel, 1887; program (Box 3)
  - 1861-1911 Jubilee anniversary of the Beaver Brook Union Sunday School, program (Box 3)
  - Fifty years of the Litchfield Northwest Sunday School Union / by John Calvin Goddard, 1913; pamphlet (Box 3)
  - Treasurer's book of the Hartford Union of Elementary Sunday School Teachers, 1907-1912; notebook (Box 3)
  - New London County Union Sunday School Institute at Norwich, Conn., 1875; program (Box 3)
  - Records of the Wethersfield and Berlin Sunday-School Union (Box 3)
    - No. 1, 1832-1866; 1 volume (Box 3)
    - No. 2, 1867-1916; 1 volume (Box 3)
  - Wethersfield and Berlin Sunday School Union programs, 1881-1916; 1 envelope (Box 3)
  - Semi-Centennial of the Wethersfield and Berlin Sunday School Union, 1832-1883, 1882; pamphlet (Box 3)
  - 2014-012
    - Bills and receipts, 1886-1897 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Reports, circa 1861-1913 (Box 11, Folder 2-4)
    - Treasury balance sheet, circa 1885-1897 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Series 3. Connecticut Sunday School Teachers Association, 1857-1896
  - Minutes of Central Committee, 1871 March 16 - 1896 December 31; pamphlet (Box 3)
    Includes Constitution of Connecticut Sunday School Association, 1826.
  - Report of the doings of the first state convention of Sabbath school teachers, held at Hartford, Conn., April 28, 29, and 30, 1857, with statistics appended, 1 volume (Box 3)
  - Report of the doings of the second state convention of Sabbath school teachers, held at New Haven, Conn., June 1,2, and 3, 1858, with statistics appended, 1 volume (Box 3)
  - Connecticut Sunday School Association, 8th-14th conventions, 1872-1884; 1 volume (Box 3)
    Back of book: First convention of the Sunday School Superintendents of Connecticut, 1885.
  - Resolutions, 1859-1860; 2014-012 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Series 4. Connecticut Sunday School Association, 1874-1923
  - Constitution and amendments, undated (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee records, 1898-1902, 1911 (Box 4)
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1902, 1905, 1911, undated (Box 4)
  - General Secretary reports, 1898-1903 (Box 4)
  - Highland Auxiliary of the Connecticut Sunday School Association minutes, 1904-1921; 2011-085; 1 volume (Box 10)
  - Normal Committee reports, 1903 (Box 4)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1897-1901 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous letters and memoranda, 1875-1919, undated (Box 4)
  - Printed material (Box 5)
    - Statistics and financial report, 1874 (Box 5)
    - Seventeenth state convention of the Connecticut Sunday-School Association, held at Danbury, Conn., November 11, 12, and 13, 1890; Proceedings of the convention, reports, addresses, papers, list of officer, etc. (Box 5)
    - Eighteenth state convention of the Connecticut Sunday-School Association, held at New Britain, Conn., November 15, 16, and 17, 1892; Proceedings of the convention, reports, addresses, papers, list of officers, etc., 3 copies (Box 5)
    - Nineteenth biennial state convention of the Connecticut Sunday-School Association, held at New London, Conn., November 13, 14, and 15, 1894; Proceedings of the convention, reports, addresses, papers, list of officer, etc., 2 copies (Box 5)
    - Report of the State Central Committee of the Connecticut Sunday-School Association for the two years ending, 1890-1898 (Box 5)
      For years ending: November 12, 1890; November 15, 1892, 2 copies; November 13, 1894; October 6, 1895, 3 copies; November 1, 1898, 6 copies.
    - Report of the State Executive Committee of the Connecticut Sunday-School Association for two years ending, 1900-1902 (Box 5)
      For years ending: November 1, 1900, 4 copies; November 1, 1902, 4 copies.
    - State convention programs, 1912-1916; 1 volume (Box 5)
    - Connecticut Sunday School Record, 1881-1897 (Box 5)
      - 1881 November 1 -1884 November 27, 1 volume (Box 5)
      - 1884 November 1 - 1886 November 20, 1 volume (Box Oversize volume)
      - 1889 March 1 - 1890 October, 1 volume (Box Oversize volume)
      - 1891 January - 1894 October, 1 volume (Box Oversize volume)
      - 1895-1897, unbound (Box 5)
        There are 3 copies of 1896.
    - Connecticut Sunday School Standard, 1912-1916 (Box 6)
      - 1912-1913, 1 volume (Box 6)
      - 1912-1913, 1 volume (Box 6)
      - 1914, 1 volume (Box 6)
      - 1915, 1 volume (Box 6)
      - 1916, 1 volume (Box 6)
    - Reports, programs and "The Standard", 1917-1923 (Box 6)
      - 1917-1921, 1 volume (Box 6)
      - 1922-1923, 1 volume (Box 6)
    - Silver Trumpet, 1907-1912; 1 volume (Box 6)
  - 2014-012
    - Correspondence, 1913 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Financial reports, 1918-1921; 3 volumes (Box Oversize volumes)
- Series 5. Connecticut Sunday School Association and Connecticut Council of Religious Education, 1912-1932
  - Minutes, 1912-1932; 2 binders, typescript (Box 7)
    Both binders contain minutes for both organizations. One binder contains Conn. Sunday School Association Executive Committee minutes, 1912-1925 and Conn. Council of Religious Education minutes, 1925-1929. The second binder contains Conn. Sunday School Association Executive Committee minutes, 1912-1924 and Conn. Council of Religious Education minutes, 1925-1932.
- Series 6. Connecticut Council of Religious Education, 1924-1934
  - Secretary's reports, 1927-1934 (Box 8)
    - 1927-1929, 1 volume, typescript (Box 8)
    - 1930-1934, 1 volume, typescript (Box 8)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1929-1932; 1 binder, typescript (Box 8)
  - Financial report (Summer school), 1927-1928 (Box 8)
    - 1927, 1 volume, typescript (Box 8)
    - 1927-1928, 1 volume, typescript (Box 8)
  - Reports and programs, 1924-1929 (Box 8)
    - 1924-1926, 1 volume (Box 8)
    - 1927-1929, 1 volume (Box 8)
- Series 7. Connecticut Council of Churches and Religious Education, 1948
  - 2014-012
    - Application for change of name - judgement, 1948 January 22 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Series 8. Connecticut Council of Churches, 1926-1974
  - 2014-012
    - Account ledgers, 1938, 1943-1947; 3 volumes (Box Oversize volumes)
    - Financial records, 1926-1974 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Professional Religious Education Association, circa 1949-1967
      - Correspondence and meeting minutes, circa 1949-1967 (Box 11, Folder 10-11)
- Series 9. Historical Material, 1853-1997
  - American Sunday school, 1921; pamphlet (Box 9)
  - Call upon the unemployed talent of the church, 1853; printed sermon (Box 9)
  - Bible teaching review, 1889; pamphlet (Box 9)
  - Church pamphlets (Box 9)
    - Center Methodist Episcopal Church, East Hartford. 25th Anniversary, 1916 (Box 9)
    - First Church of Christ, Glastonbury. Outline history of the church school, 1919 (Box 9)
    - First Congregational Church and Sunday School, Haddam. Historical sketches, 1919 (Box 9)
    - First Congregational Church, Meriden. 175th Anniversary, 1904 (Box 9)
    - First Congregational Church, Norwich Town, Conn. Calendar card, 1916 (Box 9)
    - Warburton Chapel. 50th Anniversary, 1916 (Box 9)
  - Convention pamphlets (Box 9)
    - Biennial State Sunday School Convention, 1898 (Box 9)
    - Connecticut Sunday School Teachers Associations conventions, 8th-14th, 1872-1884 (Box 9)
    - International Sunday School Conventions (Box 9)
      - 2nd, Atlanta, Georgia, 1878 (Box 9)
      - 8th, Boston, Mass., 1896 (Box 9)
    - New Jersey Sunday School Association. 55th Annual convention, 1913 (Box 9)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 9)
  - North Tolland Sunday School Association secretary's records, 1901-1913; 2011-086; 1 volume (Box 10)
  - Post card from H.H. Smith to Woodin Wallace (Box 9)
  - John T. Robinson addresses (Box 9)
    - "Value of the Sunday School from the Standpoint of a Layman" (Box 9)
    - "Duties of President" (Box 9)
  - Song "Connecticut" (Box 9)
  - Sunday School material (Box 9)
    - Congregational Sabbath School. Article from "History of Francetown, N.H." (Box 9)
    - Invitation to President and officers of Hartford Graded Union Sunday School Workers to attend conference on child welfare, 1915 (Box 9)
    - International Sunday School Association. Articles from South Carolina Sunday School Promoter (Box 9)
    - Virginia State Sunday School Association. Historical bulletin no. 1 (Box 9)
  - Sunday school superintendents (Box 9)
    - Report of the first state convention of Sunday-school superintendents of Connecticut, 1885 (Box 9)
    - Hartford Sunday School Superintendents Union. Book containing minutes, programs, etc. (Box 9)
  - Coleman's historical text-book & atlas of Biblical geography, 1854 (Box 9)
  - 2014-012
    - Cash disbursements ledger, 1947-1956; 1 volume (Box Oversize volume)
    - Cash receipts ledger, 1947-1951; 1 volume (Box Oversize volume)
    - Lectures, 1907-1918 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1981-1997, undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
      Folder includes a 20th Anniversary Partners in Community Service Award presented to Reverend Steve Sidorak on September 29, 1997; a proclamation by Hartford Mayor George A. Athanson proclaiming "April 14, 1981, as Greater Hartford Interfaith Committee for Soviet Jewry Day in the City of Hartford"; and a partial listing of "Rules of Sunday School of 1st Church."